SZYMON KLARMAN

Personal details

Born: September 18, 1981 (Poland)

Homepage: http://klarman.me szymon@klarman.me

Networks: LinkedIn, Google Scholar, Medium, Twitter, GitHub, SlideShare

Profile

An R&D specialist in **knowledge engineering** with particular interest in semantic and linked data technologies:

- ✓ 10+ years of **R&D experience** in academia and industry
- ✓ Deep interest in knowledge technologies
- ✓ Strong analytical, communication and organizational skills
- ✓ Experience in individual and team-based project work
- ✓ Enthusiasm for **learning** and exploring new problems

Expertise: knowledge engineering, knowledge representation, automated reasoning, semantics, ontologies, linked open data, graph data, algorithm design, data modelling, computational & probabilistic logics, natural language processing, statistical relational learning, prototyping

Education

2008 – 2013 Ph.D. Artificial Intelligence

Amsterdam VU University Amsterdam
Netherlands Department of Computer Science

2006 - 2008 M.Sc. Logic

Amsterdam University of Amsterdam
Netherlands Institute for Logic, Language & Computation

2000 - 2005 M.A. Philosophy

Lodz University of Lodz
Poland Institute of Philosophy

Experience

June **2018** - now Warsaw Poland

Founder & knowledge architect

Epistemik

- consulting and delivering bespoke knowledge and data engineering solutions (data models, ontologies, inference algorithms, software prototypes, etc.)
- advocating linked/graph data and semantic techniques for knowledge applications

May **2017** - Jan **2018** London United Kingdom

Knowledge architect

Semantic Integration

- devising data solutions as an onsite consultant at PhotoBox microservice architecture for managing product data (Java, DynamoDB, Stardog, ElasticSearch, GraphQL)
- initiating and leading the development of the open-source project HyperGraphQL: a GraphQL interface for guerying linked data (GraphQL, RDF, JSON-LD)
- consulting on and delivering R&D contributions towards other PoCs and prototypes (MarkLogic, GATE NLP, WEKA machine learning)

Oct **2017** - Jan **2018** CA, United States (remote)

Knowledge representation consultant

Granthika

- advising on knowledge representation and reasoning solutions
- transferring concepts from my Ph.D. work to the early product prototype
- ontology engineering and prototyping towards the PoC (Java, OWL/RDF(S))

Oct **2016** - Apr **2017** London United Kingdom

R&D engineer

Grakn Labs

- R&D work by the design and development of GRAKN a novel knowledge graph platform; involved primarily in defining and formally describing the underlying graphbased knowledge representation and reasoning model
- gathering requirements, knowledge engineering and writing data transformation scripts in the context of PoC applications (Java, Jena, OWL API)
- developing and conducting comparative benchmark tests for query and reasoning performance (Java, Jena, Prolog, Neo4j)

Feb **2015** - Oct **2016** London United Kingdom

Research fellow

Brunel University London
Department of Computer Science

- research work by the DARPA's Big Mechanism programme (goal: development of novel
 Al technology for extracting, assembling and explaining large mechanistic models
 described in the cancer biology literature to facilitate future scientific discovery)
- responsible for developing the knowledge assembly system (based on the application

of semantic and probabilistic/statistical inference tools/techniques), and maintaining the knowledge graph for the project consortium (SWI-Prolog, ProbLog, Virtuoso)

- utilizing open data & vocabularies from: UniProt, Chebi, HGNC, Pathway Commons, Gene Ontology, BioPax, PubMed, SJR, Prov-O, IAO, Dublin Core, VoID
- other independent research work (main theme: *linked data mining*)
- collaborations: University of Manchester, University of Chicago

Jul - Oct **2015** London United Kingdom

Ontology consultant

Data to Value

- ontology/taxonomy development for the financial industry domain
- knowledge graph management and data integration (unstructured, structured, linked open data) with the PoolParty semantic suite (SKOS, RDF, NLP)
- utilizing open data & vocabularies from: DBpedia, OpenCorporates, telegraphis.net, STW thesaurus. FIBO
- collaboration: Semantic Web Company

Feb **2013** - Jan **2015**

Pretoria South Africa

Postdoctoral researcher

CSIR Meraka Institute & University of KwaZulu-Natal Centre for Artificial Intelligence Research

- independent research work (main themes: ontology-based access to temporal data, abductive reasoning)
- participation in the early phases of the MomConnect project (goal: implementation of a mobile platform for supporting pregnant women in rural Africa)
- collaborations: University of Edinburgh, Jembi Health Systems

Nov 2008 - Oct 2012

Amsterdam Netherlands

Ph.D. research assistant

VU University Amsterdam

Knowledge Representation & Reasoning Group

- research work towards the doctoral degree (main theme: formal mechanisms for managing contexts in Description Logic ontologies)
- teaching responsibilities
- collaborations: University of Bremen, FBK Trento, Hewlett Packard Labs Bristol

Jul 2007 - Mar 2008

Amsterdam Netherlands

Research assistant

University of Amsterdam

Leibniz Center for Law

- research work by the ESTRELLA project (goal: development of the Legal Knowledge Interchange Format)
- knowledge and ontology engineering in the legal domain
- technical communication with the industrial partners (knowledgeTools, Rulewise BV)

Dec 2005 -Jul 2006

Dublin Ireland

Data entry operator

Millward Brown

- entering data from marketing research surveys into databases
- low level database administration and data curation

Awards & honors

2011 Best student paper

The award for the paper "Two-Dimensional Description Logics of Context" (with V. Gutierrez-Basulto) at *The 24th International Workshop on Description Logics*.

2008 Cum laude

A distinction for the overall results in the M.Sc. Logic program.

2006 - 2007 Huygens Scholarship Program

A scholarship for studying in the Netherlands awarded by the Netherlands Organization for International Cooperation in Higher Education.

2005 Thesis distinction

A distinction for the M.A. Philosophy thesis in the *Competition for Master's Theses on Logic and Its Applications*, organized by the Polish Association for Logic and Philosophy of Science and the Faculty of Mathematics, Informatics and Mechanics, University of Warsaw.

2005 Cum laude

A distinction for the overall results in the M.A. Philosophy program.

Other

Publications:

20+ publications in international, peer-reviewed journals, conferences and workshops. The full list available on my homepage and Google Scholar (200+ citations).

Community involvement:

- **Co-organizer** or **program committee** member for 10+ international conferences and workshops.
- Guest editor of a special issue of the International Journal of Approximate Reasoning.
- Reviewer for 20+ international journals, conferences and workshops.
- Visiting researcher at University of Edinburgh, FBK Trento, University of Bremen, TU Dresden.
- Invited speaker at Connected Data London Conference 2016-17, Semantic Web London Meetup 2017, Connected Data London Meetup 2016

Teaching:

- "Introduction to Description Logics" an annual, 10h course for M.Sc. Artificial Intelligence (VU University Amsterdam, 2009-2012).
- Co-supervision of 1 master's thesis and 1 minimaster's project in M.Sc. Artificial Intelligence (VU University Amsterdam, 2011).
- Philosophy and ethics classes in public schools on all levels of non-higher education (University of Lodz, 8-week internship, 2004).

Languages:

English (full professional proficiency); German, Dutch (basic, passive); Polish (mother tongue)